Marc Girons Lopez

Address Oberwiesenstrasse 50

8050 Zurich (Switzerland)

Birth 5 September 1986

Barcelona (Spain)

Website Telephone

ephone +41 (0) 78-775 89 93 E-mail gironslopez@gmail.com

gironslopez.me

Citizenship Spain

I am a hydrologist with an interdisciplinary background working as postdoctoral researcher at the University of Zurich. I aim at contributing to build up knowledge and understanding about water related issues to make society more resilient and sustainable. I believe in continuous learning and communication and I am also interested in societal behaviour and data analysis. Everything is connected!

Professional Experience

feb 2017 — aug 2018 Postdoctoral Researcher · University of Zurich (Switzerland)

My research focuses on improving the realism of the snow routine of the HBV rainfall-runoff model while maintaining a low model uncertainty. Also, I contributed to glacio-hydrological modelling of future peak flows in remote

valleys of Tajikistan.

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Graduate Teaching Assistant • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Lecturing, leading seminars, and leading and assisting in laboratory and field

activities for both undergraduate and graduate courses.

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Graduate Research Assistant • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Design and implementation of research projects within hydrology and natural disaster science, including defining research questions, modelling, data

analysis, and reporting scientific results.

jun 2009 — aug 2009 — Quality Control Intern • Laboratori Català de Control (Spain)

Quality control tests of cement, concrete and anchorages. Tests of soil properties, water sampling and analysis. Defining procedures for adopting ISO

rules.

jul 2008 — sep 2008 Environmental Consultant Intern • URS Corporation (Spain)

Environmental control tests of petrol stations, soil decontamination, and hydrogeological data processing. Fauna and sediment sampling for water

quality control of rivers and dams.

Education

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) · Uppsala University (Sweden)

Hydrology and Water Resources Science

Thesis: Information Needs for Water Resource and Risk Management:

Hydro-Meteorological Data Value and Non-Traditional Information.

aug 2009 — jun 2011 Master of Science (MSc) · Uppsala University (Sweden)

Earth Sciences (Hydrology/Hydrogeology)

Thesis: Modelling Climatic and Hydrological Variability in Lake Babati, North-

ern Tanzania.

sep 2004 — jun 2009 Bachelor of Science (BSc) · Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (Spain)

Geology

aug 2007 – jun 2008 Exchange student • Université Joseph Fourier – Grenoble I (France)

Geology and Earth Sciences

Selected Publications

(A comprehensive list of publications can be found on the website.)

Girons Lopez, M., Di Baldassarre, G., and Seibert, J. (2017). "Impact of social preparedness on flood early warning systems". In: *Water Resources Research* 53.1, pp. 522-534. ISSN: 1944-7973. DOI: 10.1002/2016WR019387.

Girons Lopez, M. and Seibert, J. (2016). "Influence of hydro-meteorological data spatial aggregation on streamflow modelling". In: *Journal of Hydrology* 541, pp. 1212–1220. ISSN: 0022-1694. DOI: 10.1016/j.jhydrol.2016.08.026.

Girons Lopez, M., Wennerström, H., Nordén, L.-Å., and Seibert, J. (2015). "Location and Density of Rain Gauges for the Estimation of Spatial Varying Precipitation". In: *Geografiska Annaler: Series A, Physical Geography* 97.1, pp. 167–179. ISSN: 1468-0459. DOI: 10.1111/geoa.12094.

Skills

Programming Python • Matlab • LATEX • Fortran

Software ArcGIS • QGIS • HBV • Git • Inkscape • Linux

InstrumentationCampbell data loggers • hydro-meteorological sensorsLanguagesNativeCatalan • Spanish

Full professional proficiency English

Professional working proficiency Swedish • French

Elementary proficiency German

Other Swedish driving license (B)

Grants, Awards, & Honours

Travel grant • Swiss Association of Geography

To participate in the first snow hydrology workshop in Finse (Norway).

2016 EGU's Photo contest • EGU

Winner of the 2016 EGU's Photo Contest with the photo Living Flows.

2015 Research Fellowship • CUAHSI

To participate in the US National Water Center Innovators Program (NFIE).

2014 Travel grant • Liljewalchs Foundation

To participate in th 2016 EGU General Assembly in Vienna (Austria).

2009 Scholarship • Swedish-Spanish Foundation

As support during my master studies.

2007 Scholarship • Erasmus Programme

To study in Grenoble (France) as an exchange student for a full year.

Other Activities

2016 — Translator • Planet Press

I translate short scientific articles for kids from the European Geosciences

Union (EGU) Planet Press initiative from English to Spanish.

2013 **Volunteer** • IAHS

I volunteered supporting the organisation of the 2013 IAHS, IAPSO, IAPSEI

Joint Assembly in Gothenburg (Sweden).

References available on request.